{
  "q1": [
    {
      "question": "A colony in this country was governed by Burnaby’s Code and faced the Spanish attack of the Battle of St. George’s Caye. George Price led this country’s People United party, where logwood was once heavily extracted by the English. This country is the site of the Mayan city of Caracol. The British maintained troops in this country after this country’s 1981 independence to deter claims from neighboring Guatemala. For ten points, name this country once known as British Honduras, which has its capital at Belmopan.",
      "answer": "Belize"
    },
    {
      "question": "Dusty Baker and Glenn Burke played for this team in 1977 when they supposedly invented the high five. Mayor Norris Poulson reversed city plans for the Elysian Park Heights public housing development in favor of giving land in Chavez Ravine to Walter O’Malley, the owner of this team. This team’s fans have a reputation for arriving late and leaving games early, in large part due to traffic nightmares on the 110 Freeway and Sunset Boulevard. For ten points, name this Major League Baseball team that, after 1957, moved from Brooklyn to Los Angeles.",
      "answer": [
        "Los Angeles Dodgers",
        "Brooklyn Dodgers after “Norris” is read"
      ]
    },
    {
      "question": "Negotiations for this treaty began after one side invoked promises made to them in the papal bull Aeterni regis. Two bulls named Inter caetera preceded this treaty and were amended by Dudum siquidem, which was rejected since it excluded John II from India. Pope Alexander VI helped mediate this treaty that granted Brazil to one party, following a demarcation line 370 leagues west of Cape Verde. For ten points, identify this treaty that divided the New World between Spain and Portugal.",
      "answer": "Treaty of Tordesillas"
    },
    {
      "question": "In a meeting with Golda Meir, this man argued that if the Soviet Union were to put Jews into gas chambers that it was “not an American concern.” This politician labeled Indira Gandhi a “witch” and claimed that “the Indians are bastards” after siding with Bangladesh in a 1971 war. In the Halloween Massacre, this man was removed as Gerald Ford’s National Security Adviser but was allowed to maintain his role as Secretary of State. For ten points, name this American statesman who won the 1973 Nobel Peace Prize for negotiating a ceasefire in Vietnam.",
      "answer": "Henry Kissinger"
    },
    {
      "question": "The Tummal Inscription verified this mythical person’s existence. Nancy Sandars’ translation of the most famous work about this man notes that Gudea may have conflated his achievements with this man. This “two-thirds divine, one-third mortal” is challenged to stay awake in order to obtain a plant that grants immortality by Utnapishtim. This man slays Humbaba in the Cedar Forest with his best friend, Enkidu. For ten points, name this protagonist of a namesake Mesopotamian epic.",
      "answer": "Gilgamesh"
    },
    {
      "question": "After being denied membership from this state’s Thule Society, Anton Arco-Valley assassinated Kurt Eisner, a leader of this state’s Soviet Republic. Ashkenazi Jews were targeted during the 1819 Hep-Hep riots in this state. Prince Liutpold ruled as regent for one monarch of this state after the latter was declared insane. The 1918 Anif declaration ended seven centuries of Wittelsbach rule over, for ten points, what German state that saw “Mad King” Ludwig II’s rule from its capital at Munich?",
      "answer": [
        "Bavaria or Bayern,",
        "descriptions of “kingdom",
        "“socialist republic”"
      ]
    },
    {
      "question": "During this period, Frank Reid was killed in a shootout with Jesse Murphy. Soapy Smith created a scam telegraph service during this period which faked its replies. Robert Henderson inadvertently sparked this period by advising Skookum Jim to explore Rabbit’s Creek. People participating in this event would often travel from Skagway before continuing on the Chikoot and White passes. Dawson City became a boom town due to, for ten points, what 19th century event in which prospectors flocked to the Yukon River?",
      "answer": [
        "Klondike Gold Rush",
        "Yukon Gold Rush before “Yukon River” is read"
      ]
    },
    {
      "question": "This man, while on assignment in the Netherlands, established the first United States embassy on foreign soil. With Edward Rutledge and Benjamin Franklin, this man negotiated the Staten Island Peace Conference with General Howe. In response to growing tensions with European countries, this President signed the Alien and Sedition Acts into law. During one election, this man was handily defeated by the newly founded Democratic-Republican party of Thomas Jefferson. For ten points, name this Federalist Founding Father, the second President of the United States.",
      "answer": "John Adams"
    },
    {
      "question": "These objects are required to have an ushnisha indentation. 6,666 of these objects rest at the feet of a giant one of these objects at the Spring Temple. An emerald one of these objects has its outfits changed by the King of Thailand each season. 504 of these objects are located at Borobudur in Java. The subjects of these objects include Amitabha and Gautama. For 10 points, name these religious objects often carved by Mahayana and Theravada followers.",
      "answer": "statues of Buddha"
    },
    {
      "question": "Zhang Chai started the “Case of the Wooden Staff Assault” by breaking into the palace of a ruler of this dynasty. The last emperor of this dynasty hung himself at the “guilty pagoda tree” and was the Chongzhen Emperor. This dynasty’s fall began after the Seven Grievances were proclaimed by Nurhachi. One emperor from this dynasty created a namesake encyclopedia and sent Zheng He to Sri Lanka. The Yongle Emperor ruled, for ten points, what dynasty that was succeeded by the Qing?",
      "answer": "Ming Dynasty"
    }
  ],
  "q2": [
    {
      "tossup": {
        "question": "In the prelude to this event, David Blair was reassigned but failed to return a storage locker key. Lord Mersey led an investigation into this event which found that J. Bruce Ismay was justified in escaping it. William Murdoch may have committed suicide near the end of this event. Wallace Hartley led a band during this event which may have played “Nearer, My God, to Thee.” Captain Edward Smith died during this event having last been seen entering the wheelhouse. For ten points, name this 1912 disaster in which an “unsinkable” ship struck an iceberg.",
        "answer": "Sinking of the RMS Titanic"
      },
      "bonus": {
        "question": "In the aftermath of the sinking of the Titanic, this woman may have forced Lifeboat No. 6 to look for survivors, earning her the nickname “Unsinkable.”",
        "answer": "Margaret “Molly” Brown"
      }
    },
    {
      "tossup": {
        "question": "Shah Ashraf Ghilji, a leader of a dynasty in this nation, beat the Safavids at the Battle of Gulnabad. Besides the Hotakis, a man known as the Iron Amir ruled this nation and crushed the Hazara revolts. This nation’s disputed border with Pakistan, the Durand Line, was established to make this nation a buffer zone between England and Russia. The Mughals disputed this country’s region of Kandahar. For ten points, name this Middle Eastern nation governed from Kabul.",
        "answer": "Afghanistan"
      },
      "bonus": {
        "question": "The political conflict between Britain and Russia for influence in Central Asia, particularly in Afghanistan, was known by this name.",
        "answer": "The Great Game"
      }
    },
    {
      "tossup": {
        "question": "This political ideology was influenced by one manifesto by Filippo Tommaso Marinetti, who argued modernization required youth, speed, and war. According to one definition, this ideology’s “goals” include a regulated economy and its “style” includes promoting masculinity, hero worship, and violence. This ideology took its name from a symbol of Roman magistrates’ authority, a bundle of sticks tied around an axe. For ten points, name this authoritarian ideology exemplified by Mussolini and Hitler.",
        "answer": "fascism"
      },
      "bonus": {
        "question": "Marinetti wrote the manifesto for this Italian artistic movement that included Giacomo Balla and Umberto Boccioni, which glorified technology and violence.",
        "answer": "Futurism"
      }
    },
    {
      "tossup": {
        "question": "This event was facilitated by the connections of Nicolas Hubbard. The arrival of minister William Vans Murray brought an end to the initial phase of this event. The Treaty of Alliance was annulled in the aftermath of this event during which one man attempted to isolate Elbridge Gerry. Charles Pinckney declared “no, no, not a sixpence!” after payment was demanded for the right to meet Charles Talleyrand. For ten points, name this event in which three French officials demanded a bribe from American diplomats.",
        "answer": "XYZ affair"
      },
      "bonus": {
        "question": "The XYZ Affair helped cause this undeclared war between the United States and France which was ended by the Convention of 1800.",
        "answer": "The Quasi-War"
      }
    },
    {
      "tossup": {
        "question": "This disaster is incorrectly attributed to “the treachery and malice of the Popish faction” on a commemorative Doric column known simply as the Monument. Thomas Bloodsworth failed to react quickly to this disaster. Thomas Farriner’s bakery on Pudding Lane may have been the starting point of this disaster, which was chronicled by Samuel Pepys [peeps]. Christopher Wren rebuilt St. Paul’s Cathedral in the wake of, for ten points, what 1666 disaster in the English capital?",
        "answer": "Great Fire of London"
      },
      "bonus": {
        "question": "Immigrants from this country were blamed for causing the fire. This country’s navy had launched the Raid on the Medway and was fighting the second of four largely naval wars with England at the time.",
        "answer": [
          "Netherlands",
          "Holland",
          "the Dutch"
        ]
      }
    },
    {
      "tossup": {
        "question": "This composer depicted his country’s industrialization in the ballet The Steel Step. Another ballet by this composer includes dances for four fairies each depicting a season. This composer of the film scores for Alexander Nevsky and Ivan the Terrible wrote a ballet containing a “Dance of the Knights.” Another work by this composer sees the bassoon represent a grandfather and the oboe represent a duck. For ten points, name this Russian composer of Peter and the Wolf.",
        "answer": "Sergei Prokofiev"
      },
      "bonus": {
        "question": "Prokofiev’s piano sonatas number 6 through 8 are collectively given this one-word nickname. This is the same word that appears in a requiem written by Benjamin Britten.",
        "answer": "war"
      }
    },
    {
      "tossup": {
        "question": "During this conflict, one leader declared “if they won’t eat, let them drink!” before throwing sacred chickens overboard at the Battle of Drepana. The Battle of the Aegates Islands was the last naval battle of this conflict, which ended with the Treaty of Lutatius. This conflict’s Battle of Mylae included the first use of a boarding bridge called the corvus. Hanno the Great and Hamilcar Barca led the losing side in, for ten points, what first major war fought between Rome and Carthage?",
        "answer": "First Punic War"
      },
      "bonus": {
        "question": "After the First Punic War, Carthage was embroiled in this conflict, named for the type of soldier who revolted due to not being paid for their service fighting Rome.",
        "answer": [
          "Mercenary War",
          "Libyan War,",
          "Truceless War"
        ]
      }
    },
    {
      "tossup": {
        "question": "This river’s estuary is spanned by a bridge which was the longest cable-stayed bridge in the world until 2004. The medieval ports of Harfleur and Honfleur controlled access to this river until the foundation of Le Havre on the mouth of this river. This river’s tributaries include the Oise [waz] and Eure rivers, and this river’s maritime section begins after it passes Rouen. The Canal Saint-Martin connects to, for ten points, what river, which is crossed by the Pont des Beaux-Arts and the Pont Neuf in Paris?",
        "answer": "The Seine River"
      },
      "bonus": {
        "question": "The departments of Seine-Maritime and Eure form the upper portion of what French region, which was given in the Treaty of Saint-Claire-sur-Epte to the first duke of this region, Rollo?",
        "answer": "Normandy"
      }
    }
  ],
  "q3": [
    {
      "category": "Mexican-American War",
      "prompt": "Name the...",
      "questions": [
        {
          "question": "US President who, following John Tyler’s work, officially annexed Texas, enraging Mexico.",
          "answer": "James Knox Polk"
        },
        {
          "question": "Treaty that ended the war in 1848.",
          "answer": "Treaty of Guadalupe Hidalgo"
        },
        {
          "question": "Port city where American troops made an amphibious landing, starting the invasion route to Mexico City.",
          "answer": "Veracruz"
        },
        {
          "question": "Major General who successfully ran for President on the strength of his victory at Buena Vista.",
          "answer": "Zachary Taylor"
        },
        {
          "question": "Resolutions introduced by Representative Abraham Lincoln, opposing war unless the government could prove American blood was shed on American soil.",
          "answer": "Spot Resolutions"
        },
        {
          "question": "April 1846 skirmish near Brownsville that sparked the war and was questioned by Lincoln; this affair is named for a US captain.",
          "answer": "Thornton Affair"
        },
        {
          "question": "Congressman who names the proposal that slavery be banned in territory gained in the war, an idea that failed in the Senate.",
          "answer": [
            "David Wilmot",
            "Wilmot Proviso"
          ]
        },
        {
          "question": "Group that fought for Mexico at Churubusco, included American deserters, and was led by Irishman John Riley.",
          "answer": [
            "Saint Patrick’s Battalion",
            "San Patricios"
          ]
        }
      ]
    },
    {
      "category": "New World Explorers",
      "prompt": "Name the...",
      "questions": [
        {
          "question": "Norseman, a descendant of Erik the Red, who settled at Vinland.",
          "answer": "Leif Erikson"
        },
        {
          "question": "Spaniard whose expedition to Florida sought the Fountain of Youth.",
          "answer": "Juan Ponce de Le´on"
        },
        {
          "question": "Spaniard whose men crossed Panama and viewed the Pacific in 1513.",
          "answer": "Vasco Nu´n˜ez de Balboa"
        },
        {
          "question": "Italian man known by an English name for his work under Henry VII [7], a 1497 expedition to Newfoundland.",
          "answer": "John Cabot or Giovanni Caboto"
        },
        {
          "question": "Breton man who mapped the Gulf of Saint Lawrence in 1534.",
          "answer": "Jacques Cartier"
        },
        {
          "question": "Explorer who “discovered” Brazil for Portugal in 1500.",
          "answer": "Pedro Alvares Cabral"
        },
        {
          "question": "Italian who mapped from Florida to New Brunswick and names a bridge connecting Brooklyn and Staten Island.",
          "answer": "Giovanni da Verrazzano"
        },
        {
          "question": "Huguenot who worked for Gaspard de Coligny, built a fort on Parris Island in South Carolina, and was murdered near Saint Augustine in 1565.",
          "answer": "Jean Ribault"
        }
      ]
    },
    {
      "category": "Assyria",
      "prompt": "Name the...",
      "questions": [
        {
          "question": "Major Mesopotamian river, east of the Euphrates, on which the empire was centered.",
          "answer": "Tigris River"
        },
        {
          "question": "Type of monument, a Black one of which was found at Nimrud, that rises to a tapered pyramidal top.",
          "answer": "obelisk"
        },
        {
          "question": "Type of institution, built by Ashurbanipal, that collected many cuneiform tablets.",
          "answer": "library"
        },
        {
          "question": "Assyrian capital city, near modern Mosul, which was sacked in 612 BC.",
          "answer": "Nineveh"
        },
        {
          "question": "Biblical prophet who goes to that capital city to warn of its destruction after being swallowed by a fish.",
          "answer": "Jonah"
        },
        {
          "question": "Late Assyrian king whose Death was famously painted by Delacroix.",
          "answer": "The Death of Sardanapalus"
        },
        {
          "question": "Father of Esarhaddon who was assassinated in 681 BC and who “came down like the wolf on the fold” in a Lord Byron poem.",
          "answer": "Sennacherib"
        },
        {
          "question": "Shared name of three Assyrian kings, the last of whom conquered Palestine and Babylon with the first Assyrian standing army.",
          "answer": [
            "Tiglath-Pileser I, II, and/or III",
            "do not"
          ]
        }
      ]
    }
  ],
  "q4": [
    {
      "parts": [
        "(30 pts) The name of an operation during this conflict was changed due to the different ways two countries spelled “Hamilcar.” This conflict’s Operation (20 pts)",
        "Musketeer featured a successful amphibious landing at Port Said [sai-eed]. Canadian Prime Minister Lester Pearson was awarded a Nobel Peace Prize for his role in resolving this conflict, which forced (10 pts)",
        "Anthony Eden to resign. This conflict included a combined Anglo-French naval assault and an Israeli attack on the Sinai Peninsula. For ten points, name this 1956 conflict which broke out after Nasser nationalized a namesake canal."
      ],
      "answer": "Suez Crisis"
    },
    {
      "parts": [
        "(30 pts) One dissent in this case criticized the majority opinion by comparing it to “ask[ing] a hippie.” This case was combined with Bourke v. Beshear, and it overturned Baker v. Nelson. John (20 pts)",
        "Kasich was the original defendant in this case, but after Sixth Circuit judge Jeffrey Sutton’s decision, this case was brought to the Supreme Court. The majority opinion of this case was written by (10 pts)",
        "Anthony Kennedy, who applied the Fourteenth Amendment to personal choices. For ten points, name this landmark Supreme Court case that legalized same-sex marriage."
      ],
      "answer": "Obergefell v. Hodges"
    },
    {
      "parts": [
        "(30 pts) This country’s July Manifesto denounced the collaborative Blue Police. A strike in this country led to the 21 Demands of MKS, and in (20 pts)",
        "1981, this country faced hunger demonstrations and a four-hour national warning strike. This country’s April Novelization followed a 1989 arrangement where 35% of the seats in the (10 pts)",
        "Sejm [same] were to be freely elected. That Round Table Agreement was primarily negotiated by a union that formed after a strike at the Lenin Shipyards in Gdansk. For ten points, name this country where Solidarity leader Lech Walesa became president."
      ],
      "answer": "People’s Republic of Poland"
    },
    {
      "parts": [
        "(30 pts) This man delivered one address upon arriving at Terowie railway station. This military commander ignored orders to execute Rainbow Five after the initial (20 pts)",
        "Pearl Harbor attacks. The first modern Purple Heart was awarded to this man, who spearheaded its reintroduction in 1932. This man fled with his wife, Jean Marie, to (10 pts)",
        "Corregidor after being expelled from Luzon by the Japanese. For ten points, name this U.S. five star general who declared “I shall return” upon escaping to Australia from the Philippines and served as Supreme Commander of Allied Forces in postwar Japan."
      ],
      "answer": "Douglas MacArthur"
    },
    {
      "parts": [
        "(30 pts) In one of this author’s novels, Phillip Herriton fails to recover his sister-in-law’s baby in Italy, where it dies in a carriage crash. In another novel by this author of (20 pts)",
        "Where Angels Fear to Trend, the main character abandons class propriety by rejecting Cecil Vane in favor of the lower class George Emerson. This author wrote a novel which was criticized for its (10 pts)",
        "colonizer-colonized friendship between Cyril Fielding and Dr. Aziz, who turns against the British Raj after being accused of rape. For ten points, name this author of A Room with a View and A Passage to India."
      ],
      "answer": "Edward Morgan “E.M.” Forster"
    },
    {
      "parts": [
        "(30 pts) The producer of the “faux Henry” in this event was eulogized after his suicide by Charles Maurras’ Action Fran¸caise and Edouard Drumont’s (20 pts)",
        "La Libre Parole, which made racist attacks against the central character in this event. That person was defended by Georges Piquart, who discovered that the “bordereau” which started this event was written by Major (10 pts)",
        "Esterhazy. One person in this event was returned from imprisonment on Devil’s Island for a retrial after Emile Zola penned J’accuse. For ten points, name this event, where a French Jewish captain was framed for treason."
      ],
      "answer": "Dreyfus Affair"
    },
    {
      "parts": [
        "(30 pts) This man developed the Banburismus method to deduce encrypted bigrams and trigrams. He proved the undecidability of the (20 pts)",
        "halting problem by creating a structure with an infinite tape of symbols, his namesake “machine.” This man committed suicide with a cyanide-laced apple after being persecuted by the (10 pts)",
        "British government. In his paper “Computing Machinery and Intelligence”, this thinker asks the question “can machines think” and proposes the imitation game, also known as his namesake test. For ten points, name this gay British computer scientist who helped crack the Enigma code."
      ],
      "answer": "Alan Turing"
    },
    {
      "parts": [
        "(30 pts) This event was preceded by a diversionary attack on Mount Holly as part of the Battle of Iron Works Hill. The Marblehead Regiment, mainly composed of (20 pts)",
        "fisherman, were key in this event but still disbanded just a few days later. Misinformation spread by John Honeyman facilitated this event. In the prelude to this event, Thomas Paine’s The (10 pts)",
        "American Crisis was read to soldiers to bolder their morale. In the fighting after the success of this event, James Monroe nearly died from a severed artery. For ten points, name this maneuver carried out by George Washington before the Battle of Trenton."
      ],
      "answer": "Washington crossing the Delaware"
    }
  ]
}